<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the famous and Godly learned man, master Iohn Caluine chiefe Minister and Pastour of Christs church at Geneua, conteining an exhortation to suffer persecution for followinge Iesus Christe and his Gospell, vpon this text following. Heb. 13. 13. Go ye out of the tents after Christe, bearing his rebuke. Translated out of French into english,</title>
            <title>Quatre sermons avec exposition du Pseaume 87. English. Sermon 2. Selections</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4439.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116257</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851474</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16748</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16748)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1657:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the famous and Godly learned man, master Iohn Caluine chiefe Minister and Pastour of Christs church at Geneua, conteining an exhortation to suffer persecution for followinge Iesus Christe and his Gospell, vpon this text following. Heb. 13. 13. Go ye out of the tents after Christe, bearing his rebuke. Translated out of French into english,</title>
                  <title>Quatre sermons avec exposition du Pseaume 87. English. Sermon 2. Selections</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Fielde, John, d. 1588.</author>
                  <author>I. P., fl. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert VValdegraue for Edward VVhite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The second half, beginning B3r line 18, is part of the same translation as sermon 2 in STC 4439--STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "An answere to the slaunders of the papistes against Christs syllie flock", which is in verse and signed I.P.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A godly sermon of M. Iohn Caluine.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXVII --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English16th century.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16748:1"/>
            <p>A Sermon of the famous and Godly learned man, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Iohn Caluine, chiefe Miniſter and Paſtour of Chriſts church at Geneua, conteining an exhortation to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for followinge Ieſus Chriſte and his Goſpell, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this Text fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Go ye out of the Tents af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Christe, bearing his rebuke.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French into english,</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert VValdegraue for <hi>Edward VVhite.</hi> 1581.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16748:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16748:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON of the Famous and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>learned man,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iohn Caluine, Chiefe miniſter and <hi>Pastour of Christes Church at</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua, conteining an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 13.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Go ye out of the Tents after Christ, bearing his rebuke.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll exhortations that a man maye make to vs, of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring patiently for the name of Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">A conſtant man in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is knowne by the certenty of the word whereupon he ſtandeth</note> and for the quarrell of the Goſpell, they ſhall haue no place, if we bee not very well aſſured of the cauſe, for the which wee doe contend, for when the queſtion is of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the life, it is requiſit, that we be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and certaine, wherefore it is. And ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:16748:3"/>
conſtancie cannot bee in vs, vnleſſe it bee grounded on the certeinty of fayth. True it is, that a man ſhall finde out ſome that will ſubmit themſelues fooliſhly to death,<note place="margin">Stubbornes in opinion beſides the word, is fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie.</note> For to mainteine certeine fond opinions, &amp; fantaſies, which they ſhall conceiue in their head, but ſuch an earneſtneſſe deſerueth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee counted for frenſie, then for a Chriſtian zeale, like as in deede, there is neither conſtancy neither approued iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſuch people, who gaue themſelf, ſo to ſtubbornneſſe, Sithen this is ſo, there is nothing but a good cauſe, which maketh that God accepteth vs for his Martyrs: for death is common to all.<note place="margin">A good cauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</note> And the children of God ſhall be condemned to ſuch ſhame and torments as though they were theeues. But God putteth a difference betweene them, in ſo much that he can not deny this verity.<note place="margin">the children of God are put to villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this worlde.</note> Therfore it is requiſit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on our part we haue ſure vndoubted teſtimony of the do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine, which we doe ſuſtaine. For as much as I haue ſayd we can not bee moued, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touched with a good intention, for any exhortations that any body make to vs, to ſuffer perſecution for the Goſpel, if ther be not a true certeinty of faith grauen in our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16748:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hearts,<note place="margin">A man can not ſuffer perſecution for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vnleſſe fayth be grauen in his heart, for to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard our life it is not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall but temeritie.</note> for to hazarde our life at all aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is not natural. And when we ſhal ſo do, that ſhall be but temerity, and no Chriſtian vertue at all, at length God will approue nothing at alll that wee ſhall do vnleſſe we be well peeſuaded, that it is for his ſake, and for his cauſe, that men doe moleſt vs, and that the world is our enemy Now when I ſpeake of ſuch a certeinty, I do not meane only that we know to deſern betweene true religion, and the abuſes or follies of men.</p>
            <p>But alſo that we be well perſuaded of the life celeſtiall, and of the crowne whiche is there promiſed vs, after that we haue ſtriuen here beneath. In the meane while note that both theſe two points be requiſit,<note place="margin">VVe muſt be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the life celeſtiall and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to come.</note> and that no man ought to ſeperate the one from the other, it is meete therefore for vs to begin at this point, to knowe well what our Chriſtanitye is, what the fayth is which we muſt mayntein and follow, what is the rule that God hath giuen vs,<note place="margin">Too points neceſſary in religion to be knowen.</note> and that we be defended with ſuch inſtruction, that we can boldly condemn all falſe lies, errors and ſuperſtitions, whiche the diuell hath brought in for to corrupt the pure ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:16748:4"/>
of the doctrine of God: wherefore a man muſt not be amazed if he ſee not at this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent day,<note place="margin">VVhy men commonly refuſe the Croſſe of that.</note> very many perſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be diſpoſed for the goſpell to ſuffer, &amp; that the greateſt part of thoſe which name themſelues Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, knoweth not what it is. For al be in manner negligent, &amp; make no account, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her to heare, neither to reade, but it is y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them that they haue had a little taſte of the fayth of Chriſte, beholde then, wherefore there be ſo few of others, but if they be aſſaulted, they wil by and by run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. This ought to ſtirre vs vp to enquire more diligently of the trueth of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we might be certein therof. But yet this is not al,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The want of zeale and loue to the trueth, is the cauſe why men refuſe to ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to vs in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               </note> that we ſhould be taught wel and haue intelligence, for we may ſee, ſuch as ſeeme to be perfect in good doctrine, the which notwithſtanding haue neither zeal, neither affection in them, no more then if they had neuer knowen any thing of God, but after ſome fantaſticall will. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that, but in as muche they neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comprehended the maieſty of the holy ſcripture. And in deede, if we all to gether conſidered well, that it is God which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to vs, it is moſt certeine that we ſhold
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16748:4"/>
be more attentiue to hearken to the ſame, and with a great reuerence, when we in rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the ſcripture doe think that we are at the ſchole of Angelles,<note place="margin">The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the ſchole of Angelles.</note> we ſhal ſtraite haue another care, and deſire to exerciſe vs in that doctrin which is ſet before vs, now we ſeeing that it is the meane to prepare vs to ſuffer for the goſpel, that is, that we haue ſo farre profited in the ſchole of God, that wee being aſſured of the true religion and doctrine which we ought to holde, we may auoyd all the craftes and ſubtelties of the Diuel, and all mans inuentions,<note place="margin">Note howe a true mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr is known from the falſ</note> as things not onely of no effect, but alſo accurſſed, in as much as they corrupt Chriſtian puritie: and in this point we as true Martyrs of Ieſus Chriſt do differ from theſe bedlems that ſuffer for their fooliſh opinions. Secon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>darily, that wee being certeine of the good cauſe, be enkendled, as it is conueniente to followe God whereto ſoeuer he calleth vs, that his word hath ſuch authority with vs, as it is worthy, and that we being w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worlde, be in maner rauiſhed to ſeek after the celeſtiall life. But this is a thing very ſtraunge, that the brightneſſe of God ſhineth at this day ſo playnly, as it did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:16748:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more, and yet there be very fewe that haue a zeale thereto whiche is lamentable, and if we bee not aſhamed hereof, it is ſo much the worſe for vs, for wee muſt come ſhortly before the great Iudge, where that euill which we go about to couer, ſhal be ſet before vs with ſuch reproch, that there wil be found ſufficient cauſe to caſt vs downe altogether to the pit of hell, For if we bee bounde to render teſtimony to God, alter the meſure of the knowledge which he hath giuen vs, to what tendeth it I praye you, that we are ſo colde and fearefull,<note place="margin">VVe are bound to confeſſe our fayth.</note> for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to this combat, ſithen that God is in ſuch ſort reuealed to vs at this time, that a man may ſay that he hath diſcloſed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the great treaſures, of his ſecretes, may it not be well ſayde that we will not haue any thing to doe with God, for if wee had any regard of his maieſtie, we woulde not bee ſo bolde as to turne the doctrine which proceedeth out of his mouth into a certeine Phyloſophy or ſpeculation, I can not tel what. To be ſhort, ther is no excuſe but this is to our greate ſhame, and rather to our horrible condemnation that we haue had ſo much knowledge of the truth of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16748:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
&amp; haue ſo litle corage to ſtand to the ſame. Ouer al, when wee conſider the martirs in times paſt,<note place="margin">Courage to ſtand is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit with knowledge. The faith of Martyrs in pime paſt.</note> we may wel abhorre the vilany which is in vs, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not much exerciſed in the holy ſcripture, for to haue knowledge, to diſpute of all things, they know that there was one God alone, whome men ought to worſhippe and ſerue Alſo that they were redemed by the blood of Ieſus Chriſte to this ende, to put their truſt of ſaluation in him, and in his grace, &amp; that all that which hath bine found out by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was not to be eſteemed, &amp; were able therby to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn al idollatry &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumme of their diuinitie was this, ther is one onely God, who hath created all the world, &amp; hath declared vs his wil by <hi>Moſes</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets, &amp; laſt of all by Ieſus Chriſte &amp; his Apoſtles, we haue one only redeemer who hath redeemed vs by his bloode, and grace, wherby we truſt to be ſaued. Al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles of the world be accurſſed &amp; execrable hauing nothing but this, they went frankly either to the fier or els to any other kind of deathe. And this was not done by two or three, but in ſo great multitudes, that the number of thoſe whiche bee dead by the
<pb facs="tcp:16748:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
handes of Tyrantes is in manner infinite, we are of our part ſo great Clearks, that none can be more,<note place="margin">Now a days much know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and litle zeale.</note> (at leaſt ſo we think,) &amp; in deede as concerning the vnderſtanding of the ſcripture, God hath dealt ſo largely with vs as euer he hath don with any age. Yet not with ſtanding there is ſcarce one drop of zeal. Now to make much of ſuch a feeblenes, it is to no purpoſe, vnles we wil willingly prouoke the vengeaunce of God,<note place="margin">Note what is to be done to haue a courage to ſuffer.</note> what ſhall we then doe, for to take a good courage. Firſt of al we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how this thing is pretious before God, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith, for we knowe it ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, howe God alloweth the ſame ſince our life, which is verye nothing, is more eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of vs: In the which we declare a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous beſtialitie, for we can not ſpare our life in this cauſe, but wee muſt confeſſe that the ſame is more beloued of vs then the honor of God, and the ſaluation of our ſoules. A certaine painime could well ſaie, that it was a miſerable thing for a man to put awaie the cauſes wherfore he doth liue to ſaue his life, neuertheles he and ſuch like neuer knew to what ende men were ſet in the worlde, and for what cauſe they liue. It
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16748:6"/>
is true that they had good knoweledge to ſay that a man ought to follow vertue, that a man ought to behaue him ſelfe honeſtlie,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Our life is to glorifie God.</p>
                  <p>The prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our life beſides Gods wil is malediction</p>
               </note> and without reproche: but all their vertues were but colours &amp; ſmokes, we know much better, to what our life ought to be imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: that is to glorifie God, to the end hee might be our glory, without this the woe is ouer vs, and we can not prolong our life, as much as one minute more of time on the earth, in the which wee doe bring ſo muche the more malediction vpon our own heads. Notwithſtanding we are not aſhamed, to purchaſe here in this world a certaine few daies, for vs to lament in, renouncing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the euerlaſting kingdome, ſeperating our ſelues from him, by whoſe vertue we are maintained in life. If a man demand of the verieſt ignorant perſons, or els of the moſt bruteſt of the world, for what cauſe is it that they liue, they dare not ſimply ſaye that it was, to eate, drinke, and ſleepe,<note place="margin">The ende of our life is to honor God, and to bee ruled by his word.</note> for al men do knowe that they were created to a more noble and more excelent end, &amp; what end can we finde els but to honor God, and to ſuffer our ſelues to be ruled by him, as children of a good father, to the intent that
<pb facs="tcp:16748:7"/>
after we haue ended the viage of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible life, we may be receiued into his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall inheritaunce, beholde this is the principall cauſe of our life, and the ſelfe ſame altogether, when we make account thereof that we are incarnated to a beaſtly life, the which is worſſe then a thouſande deathes, what may we allege for our expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for to liue, and not to knowe, wherfore it is againſt nature plainly. And to reiect the cauſes, for the which we liue, vnder the pretence of a fooliſhe appetite, for to haue a certaine reſpite of three daies, to the end to dwel in the world being ſeperate from god, I can not tell how a man ſhall call ſuche a frenſie and rage. But becauſe perſecutions doe not ceaſe, to be grieuous, and bitter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, marke how this commeth to paſſe, &amp; by what meanes Chriſtians might ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them ſelues to patience, euen to yeeld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly their life for Gods verity the text which we haue recited,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> when it ſhal be vnder ſtood, is ſufficient inough for to induce vs to the ſame, <hi>Let vs go out of the country</hi> (ſaith the apoſtle) <hi>after the Lorde Ieſus, bearing his reproche,</hi> In the firſt parte, he exhorteth vs, although the ſwords be not redie drawn
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16748:7"/>
vppon vs, nether the fires kindled to burn vs, that we can not truelie be ioyned to the ſonne of God, whileſt that we be engraffed in this worlde,<note place="margin">A perſon of God muſt haue his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drawn from the world.</note> wherfore it is requiſite that a chriſtian perſon being him ſelfe at reſt, hath alwayes one foote lift vp to go to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle, and not onely that, but that hee hath his affection withdrawne from the worlde, albeit the body dwelleth here. Although this ſeemeth to vs a rude thing, at the firſt looking, yet we ſhoulde bee well contented with this ſaying of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.</note> which is that we are called and appointed to ſuffer, as who woulde ſay, that the condition of our Chriſtianity, is in ſuch ſorte, that we muſt paſſe by this way, if we will follow Ieſus Chriſte, In the meane while for to comfort our infirmitie, and to make ſweete the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſſe and ſorowfulneſſe,<note place="margin">Note our comfort in perſecution.</note> whiche perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions might bring vs, beholde a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, which is, that we in ſuffering for the Goſpell doe follow as it were, ſtep after ſtep, the ſonne of God, and we haue him for oure guide, if it had beene ſayde ſimplye of vs, that for to bee Chriſtians, wee muſt paſſe through the ſhames of the worlde, and muſt come courageouſly
<pb facs="tcp:16748:8"/>
vnto death, as many times, &amp; as often as it ſhall pleaſe God, wee might haue (as it ſeemeth) ſome coulers to reply, that this is a thing very ſtraunge to make on ſtray away.<note place="margin">VVe muſt be like to the image of Chriſte.</note> But where it is comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs to fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe the Lord Ieſus, his conduct is too good and honorable for vs to refuſe. Now to the end that we might be the better mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it is not only ſayde, that Ieſus goeth before vs as our captaine, but alſo that we be made like to his image, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh thereof, the eight Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> That God hath ordeined all thoſe whom he hath choſen, for his children, for to be made conformable to him, who is the patron and head of vs al, are we ſo delicate that we will not ſuffer nothing, it behoueth vs to declare the grace of God, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he hath called vs vnto the hope of ſaluation For theſe be two things that can not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated,<note place="margin">Two things neceſſary in a Chriſtian, we may not regard the ſhame of the world in Chriſtes cauſe.</note> for to be the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Ieſus Chriſt and to be exerciſed with many afflictions. Certeinly we ought a great deale more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſuch a conformitie with the ſonne of God, then we otherwiſe doe, It is true that after the iudgement of the world, it is ſhame to ſuffer for the Goſpell, but ſithen
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16748:8"/>
that wee knowe that the faythleſſe bee blynde, ſhoulde wee not haue better eyes then they,<note place="margin">Acts. 5.</note> It is ignominy to be affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which occupy the ſeat of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth vs by his example that wee haue to glory in the woundes of Ieſus Chriſt, as in the marks. by the which God acknowledgeth, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth vs for his. And we know what S. <hi>Luke</hi> reherſeth of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> that is, how they reioyced of that they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to ſuffer infamy and reproch for the name of the Lorde Ieſus, beholde two contrary things, Ignominy, and dignity:<note place="margin">It is a digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a Chriſtian man to ſuffer</note> verily for as the world is fooliſh, it iudgeth againſt al reaſon &amp; by this means conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the glory of God, to diſhonour, Then of our part, let vs not refuſe to be diſpiſed before the worlde, that we may be honored before God, and his angels, We ſee what paine ambitious men do take for to obtain the order of a King, and what triumphes, they make therein. The ſonne of God offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs his order, and euerye body refuſeth it. I pray you in this doing are we worthie to haue any thing commen with him? our ſenſualitie can not bite here, but is of ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:16748:9"/>
balure that the ſame, be the verye bages of our noblenes, impriſonment, baniſhment &amp; curſſings, do not bring after mans fancies, but all reproche:<note place="margin">Looke not in thy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble what the world iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, but what God iudgeth.</note> but what letteth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde that which God iudgeth thereof and pronounceth but onely our infidelity, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it, that the name of the ſonne of god hath ſuch importance with vs, as it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to the ende, we ſhould learne to take to honor, that hee printeth in vs his marks, otherwiſe our vnthankefulnes is not to be borne. If God ſhould puniſhe vs after our demerits, hath he not daily iuſt occaſion to chaſtiſe vs in a thouſand ſorts. Moreouer then this, a hundred thouſand deathes were not ſuffitient for a little portion of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings, yet by his infinite goodnes, he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnder foote al our treſpaſſes, and doth them away, and in ſteede of puniſhing vs according to that we haue deſerued, he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a wonderfull meanes for to make the afflictions to be turned to our honor, and into a ſpeciall priuelege,<note place="margin">By affliction we are made companions with Chriſt.</note> in ſo much that by the ſame we are aſſociate into the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of his ſonne may it not well bee ſaied when we diſdain ſo bleſſed a condicion, that we haue very euill profited in the doctrine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16748:9"/>
of Chriſt, Beholde why ſaint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Peter 4.</note> after he had exhorted vs ſo holily in the feare of God, that we ſhould not ſuffer as theeues, whoremongers, and murtherers, he addeth howe and in what manner: let vs ſuffer as Chriſtians that wee might glorifie God for the good which he doth to vs.<note place="margin">To defende the veritie is an honor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Aungels.</note> It is not without cauſe that he ſpeaketh in this wiſe for what are we I pray you, to be witneſſes to the verity of God, &amp; procurers to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine his cauſe, Behold here pore wormes of the earthe, creatures full of vanitye alltogether, and yet God willeth vs, that we defend his verity, which is an honour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perteineth not to the very aungelles of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe? Ought not this conſideration alone ſo much to enflame vs to offer our ſelues to God, for that which pleaſeth him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vs to ſo honourable a thing: not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding many can not refrain themſelues to encounter againſt God, or at the leaſt to make their complaintes of this, that God doeth not bear better with their weaknes.<note place="margin">An aunſwer to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of of weaklings 1. Peter. 1.</note> This is meruelous ſay they, ſince that God hath choſen vs for his children, how can he abide it that we bee thus defiled and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the wicked, I aunſweare, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:16748:10"/>
it doth not appear to vs, wherefore he doth it, yet it ſhould haue this authority with vs to make vs walke after his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But when we looke in our patern Ieſus Chriſte, ought not wee to iudge it a great felicity, for to be made like vnto him without any further queſtion, Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God ſheweth vs cauſes very eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, for the which he willeth vs to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Peter. 1.</note>If ther were none other reaſon but that S. <hi>Peter</hi> maketh, we were very co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if wee woulde not bee content therewith, that is, ſince that gold and ſiluer, which be not but corruptible mettalles bee purged and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the fire,<note place="margin">It is the will of God vve ſhould ſuffer perſecution.</note> it is good reaſon that our fayth which ſurmounteth all the riches of the worlde be proued. God might haue crouned vs as at the firſte brunte without making vs to ſuſtain any conflict: but hee willeth that Ieſus Chriſte doth rayn in the middeſt of his enemies, ſo hee willeth that we being iugled in the middes of them, ſhould ſuffer their oppreſſions and violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vntill that he deliuer vs from the ſame. I knowe wel that the fleſh reigneth when we goe aboute to bring it to this poynte,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16748:10"/>
but it is requiſit,<note place="margin">It is naturall for vs to flee the Croſſe but vve muſt ſubdue that affection.</note> that the will of God haue the vpper hand. If we feele any contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in vs, we muſt not be amaſed thereat, for this is a right naturall thing to flee the croſſe, neuertheleſſe, we may not goe anye further, knowing that God doth accept our obedience, ſo that we do ſubdue and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſences and deſires for to make them ſubiect vnto him: for the Apoſtles and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets went not in ſuch wiſe to death, that they felt not in themſelues,<note place="margin">Iohn. 21.</note> a certeine will to go back, <hi>another man ſhal lead thee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wouldest not</hi> (ſayde Lorde Ieſus Chriſt to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The battell of a criſtian man.</note>) Likewiſe when ſuch fear of death doth pricke vs, it is a gaine for vs to heauenward, or rather God winneth vs thereby, or in the mean time let vs be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that this is a Sacrifice prayſing him: that we doe reſiſt and make force agaynſt our affections, for to bee altogether at his commaundement, and this is the principal battell in the which God willeth that his people doe employ themſelues, which is, that they endeuour to beate downe all that lifteth it ſelfe vp in their ſences and ſpirits, for to turne them oute of the way, whiche he ſheweth them, and with all this, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations
<pb facs="tcp:16748:11"/>
be ſo great that it muſt needs be ſayd, that we are more then cowards when we do faint. In old time an infinite number of people, for the deſire of a ſimple crowne of leaues, they refuſed not any trauell, trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble or payne for the ſame, they counted it nothing to dye,<note place="margin">The crowne of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſuch as do ſuffer.</note> notwithſtanding there was none of them, but did fyght at al aduenturs not knowing whether he ſhould winne the price or not, God hath ſette before vs the Crowne of immortality, by the which wee are made partakers of his glory, he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not that we ſhoulde fight at all aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> but promiſeth vs all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price that haue a deſire thereof, what occaſion haue wee to come to heauen, do we think that it is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vain,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> that if we dye with Ieſus Chriſt, wee ſhall liue alſo with him. The triumph is prepared, and wee flee the Combat as much as lyeth in vs. This is a doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to mans iudgement, I do confeſſe the ſame, and alſo when Ieſus pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that thoſe which ſuffer for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be bleſſed, hee proponeth not a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whiche is eaſie to bee receiued of the worlde. Contrariwiſe hee willeth vs to repute that for felicity which the world and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16748:11"/>
our ſences iudgeth vnhappy.<note place="margin">VVhom the vvorldlye counteth miſerable are moſt happie.</note> It ſeemeth vs that we are miſerable when God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth vs to bee deſtroyed by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and cruelty of our enemies, but the faulte is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no regard at all to the promiſes of God, the which do certefie vs that all ſhall be turned to our good, we are diſcouraged to ſee the wicked to bee ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and to hold their foote vpon our throte. but ſuch a confuſion (as ſaith Saint <hi>Paule</hi>) ought rather to lift vs vp on high,<note place="margin">Note vvhy the euill do proſper and the good troubled.</note> for in as much we are giuen of our ſelues too much to muſe vpon the thinges preſent. God in permitting the good folke, to bee euill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, and the wicked to haue there will, he teacheth vs by manifeſt tokens that one day will come, in the which all that is now confuſed ſhalbe reformed. If the time ſeeme long vnto vs, let vs runne to the remedie, and not flatter our ſelues in our vice: for it is certeine, that we haue no fayth at all, vnleſſe we lift vp the eyes of our ſoules to the comming of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">our eie muſt be fixed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt.</note> Nowe God to the end he mighte leaue no meane vnattempted, which might be fyt to driue vs forward, he ſetteth before vs the promiſes on the one ſide, and his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
<pb facs="tcp:16748:12"/>
on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other.<note place="margin">VVe muſt haue both the promiſes and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of god before our eies in our troubles. Math. 10. Luke 12.</note> Do we think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes haue not power enogh in vs? let vs ioin the threatnings for to ſtrengthen them. It is very true, that wee muſt be ſo muche the more peruerſe and froward, not to adioyne more fayth then we doe to the promiſes of God, when the Lorde Ieſus ſayth, that he will auow and acknowledge vs before his father, ſo that we confeſſe him before men. and what is there that ought to let vs, that we ſhould not yeld him that confeſſion that he requireth. When men ſhall haue done their vttermoſt, they can doe no worſe but murther vs. And what ſhall eternall life be in comparſon thereof? I heape not vp here al the promiſes conteined in the ſcriptures whiche tende to one and the ſame end: yet (foraſmuch as they are ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) wee ought wholy to ſtay vppon them. But if when the plague hang ouer our heades, if three or foure bee not ynough, one whole hundred will not ſerue to make vs to ouercome all aduerſity and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye temptations. But if God can drawe vs vnto himſelfe thorough gentleneſſe, muſte wee not bee more then beetle block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh heades, when his ſeuere threatnings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16748:12"/>
can doe no more therein? Ieſus Chriſte citeth all thoſe before his father,<note place="margin">Chriſt doeth ſommon all them that denie his trueth. Math 10. Math. 10.</note> who ſhall through fear of bodily death deny the truth: and ſayth, that both the body and ſoule, ſhal be throwne to perdition, And in another place he ſayth, that he will deny all thoſe that ſhal deny him before men, vnleſſe that we be to much bereued of al vnderſtanding theſe wordes ought to make our hair ſtand vpright vpon our heads, Howſoeuer it be, when we ſhall not be moued therewith as were meet, there remaineth nothing for vs but an horrible confuſion: For in that,<note place="margin">VVhen nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes nor threatnings do moue confuſion remaineth.</note> that all the wordes of Ieſus Chriſt doe ſo little profite vs, we are conuinced of too greate infidelitie. We ſhal haue alledged too god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſe that there is ſome pitty in vs, foraſmuch as our nature is ſo brittie: For it ſayde contrariwiſe that <hi>Moſes</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto God through fayth, was ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened not to bowe vnder any tentation.<note place="margin">Heb. 11. An anſwere to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of fraielnes of nature.</note> Wherefore when we are ſo ſoft and flexible yea, that ther is no zeal &amp; conſtancie in vs, it is a ſigne that we are vtterly ignorannt both of God and his kingdome. When it is ſhewed vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought to be ioined to our hed, we think that we haue a goodly couler
<pb facs="tcp:16748:13"/>
to exempt ourſelues from it, by ſaying that we are men. But they which haue gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, who were they? It is true that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhall not haue the pure doctrine, all the excuſes that we can bring forth ſhalbe vain: but hauing ſo many examples which ought to ſerue for the greater approbation, ſo muche the more are we to bee condemned. But heere we haue two pointes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.<note place="margin">The church of Chriſt is continually ſubiect to afflictions. Pſal. 129.</note> The firſt is, that all the body of the Church generally, was and ſhal be always ſubiect till the ende, to bee afflicted by the wicked: as it is ſayd in the Pſalme. <hi>They haue vexed me from my youth vp, they haue drawne the Plow vpon me from one ende to an other.</hi> The holy Ghoſte bringeth in the old Church ſpeaking, to the end that we, after we haue knowen the afflictions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we ſhould not finde it ſtraunge or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome if the like at this day be done vnto vs. S. <hi>Paule</hi> alſo drawing this place from another Pſalme where it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. Pſal. 44.</note> 
               <hi>We haue bene as Sheepe that are led to the ſlaughter,</hi> ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this was not for one age alone: but that it is and ſhall be ordinarily and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall in the Church. Seeing the Church of God to be at this day troaden vnder, by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16748:13"/>
pride of worldlinges, that one barketh,<note place="margin">The ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Church.</note> another byteth, that men torment it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes miſchieuouſly deuiſe againſt it, that without ceaſing it is aſſayled of mad dogs and ſauadge beaſtes: let vs remember that this was done vnto it of olde time. It is true that God may well giue it ſometimes certeine truces and releaſements. And this is it that is ſayde in the Pſalme before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged,<note place="margin">The end of afflictions is bliſſe.</note> 
               <hi>be cutteth aſunder the Cords of the wicked.</hi> And in another place, that he will breake their ſtuffe, for feare that the good doth not ouermuch vexe themſelues, being too much oppreſſed. But God woulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that his Church ſhould be toſſed in this worlde, and be as it were in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall conflict, reſeruing reſt for it aboue in the heauens, Notwithſtanding that yet the iſſue of theſe afflictions was alwaies bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and at the leaſt God broughte to paſſe, that being oppreſſed with many euilles, it was neuer vtterly oppreſſed, as it is ſayde that the wicked with all their forces neuer attayned to that which they immagined:<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.</note> S. Paul alſo reioyceth himſelfe of the like to ſhewe, that this is a continuall grace of God: <hi>We</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>endure tribulations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor 4.</note> 
               <hi>but
<pb facs="tcp:16748:14"/>
we are not therewith distreſſed, we are pore but we are not destitute: we are perſecuted but we are not forſaken: we are cast downe but we periſh not, euery where bering about in our bodies the dying of our Lorde Ieſus, to the end that his life may be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in our mortal bodies,</hi> Such iſſue as wee ſee that God hath giuen at al times in the perſecutions of his Church, ought well to encourage vs, knowing that our fathers, who were brickle men as we are, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the victory ouer their enimies: in as much as they remayned ſtedfaſt in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But I do but touch this point briefly to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ende I may come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond,<note place="margin">Secondarily vvee muſt looke vpon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler examples of martirs vvhich haue bene before vs. Heb. 12.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which more agreeth to our purpoſe: that it is to make our profite of thoſe particular exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Martyrs, which haue gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs.</p>
            <p>Now there are not onely two or three of them, <hi>but a thicke and great cloude,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayth in the epiſtle to the Hebr. Whereby he ſignifieth that the number is ſo great, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ought as it were euen to ſtop vp our eyes. And that I be not to tedious, I will take onely the example of the <hi>Iewes</hi> which were perſecuted for true religion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16748:14"/>
as well vnder the Tyranny of <hi>Antiocbus</hi> the King, as alſo a little after his death. We cannot alleage that it was a ſmal num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of people: for there were then as it wer a great army of martyrs. Wee cannot ſay that it was of Prophets, whome God had ſeperated from the common people: for the women and yong infants were of this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany. We cannot ſay that they were let go for any pryſe: for they were tormented as cruelly as was poſſible. We hear alſo that which the Apoſtle ſheweth vs of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>were hanged vp like belles and racked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>making no account to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the ende they might receiue a better reſurrection. Others were tried by mockings and ſcourgings: yea by bondes and priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: others were stoned or hewen aſunder:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the faithfull in the olde law and vs.</note> 
               <hi>other wandred vp and down hither and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in Wildernes by mountains and Caues.</hi> Let vs nowe enter to make compariſon of them with vs. If they ſuffered for the truth of God, whiche was yet ſo darke at that time, what ought wee to doe in this greate lighte that ſhineth nowe? God hath ſpoken vnto vs as it were with a full mouth, the great Gate of the kingdome of heauen is
<pb facs="tcp:16748:15"/>
opened, Ieſus Chriſte hath called vs vnto him, beeing come down vnto vs, to the end that we ſhoulde haue him as it were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent before our eies. And what a ſhame ſhal it be vnto vs to haue leſſe zeale to ſuffer for the Goſpel then they had, which onely ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and behelde the promiſes of God, as it were a farre off? Whiche had but a little Wicket open to come to the kingdome of heauen? which had nothing but a certeine remembrance and figure of Ieſus Chriſte? Theſe thinges cannot bee expreſſed with mouth as they are woorthy: wherefore I leaue them for euery one to meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VVe ought to prepare our ſelues to the Croſſe although we be in no daunger thereof.</note>Now this doctrine as it is generall, ſo ought it to be put in practiſe of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: But euery one ought to apply it to his owne vſe as neceſſity ſhall require. I ſpeak this to the ende that they which ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in no apparant daunger, ſhoulde not thinke that it is ſuperfluous vnto them. They are not at this time in the handes of Tyrantes: but what knowe they how God will deale with them hereafter Wherefore we ought to be ſo armed afore hand, that if any perſecution, which we haue not thoght
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16748:15"/>
vpon, ſhall come vpon vs, we be not taken at vnwares and vnprouided.<note place="margin">Howe he ought to be haue him ſelf that is vnder perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</note> But I feare me that there are a great ſort of deafe ears to heare this worde. So farre off is it, that they which are nice and liue at their eaſe, prepare them ſelues to ſuffer death when need ſhal be, that they haue no care to ſerue God whiles they liue. And yet neuertheles this ought to be our ordinary and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtudy, and ſpecially in this time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue. In the meane time they whome God hath called to ſuffer for the teſtimonye of his name, ought to ſhew in very deede that they were prepared long before, too ſtande thereto conſtantly. And then they ought to cal into their remembrance al the exhortations that they haue hard in times paſt: as if a ſouldier ſhoulde take armes when the Trumpet doeth ſound. But what there is no queſtion of ſeeking ſtarting holes to eſcape:<note place="margin">Perſecution is the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by god doth diſcouer his people.</note> I ſpeake in reſpect of the greateſt parte: For perſecution is a true touchſtone whereby God diſcouereth and trieth who are his. So farre of is it, that he ſhoulde many times finde who is faythfull vnto him, vntill that they franckly offer themſelues to death. But this is as it were
<pb facs="tcp:16748:16"/>
an incredible thing, that people whiche boaſt of ſome little knowledge of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">Cauilations of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Mar. 8. VVe muſt confeſſe Chriſt is truth before the wicked. VVe muſt commit our life to the handes of God.</note> dare open their mouth to vſe ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilations. For one ſort ſay, what ſhall wee game to confeſſe our faith to obſtinate peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to ſuche who haue determined to fight agaynſt God? Is not this to caſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones before ſwine, As though Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt had not expreſly declared that he will y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men confeſſe him amongſt the moſte peruerſe &amp; wickedſt men. If they be not therby edefied, yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt they remain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>founded: of ſuch a ſweet ſmelling ſauour is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before god, how deadly ſoeuer it be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate. Others alſo may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d who ſay, what ſhall our death profit? It ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falleth out to an offence, as if God had left to their choiſe to die when they thinke good, and when they ſhall ſee a fit time. But contrariwiſe wee approue oure obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, leauing the profit into his hand that ſhall come of our death. Wherefore in the firſt place, it behoueth that a chriſtian man, in what country ſoeuer he be, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding daungers and threatninges, that hee fully determine to walke in ſimplicity, as God hath commaunded, Let him keep him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16748:16"/>
ſelfe aſmuch as he can from the rage of the Wolues: ſo that the ſame be not done tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the crafte of the fleſh. Aboue all let him reſign his life into Gods hands. Hath he done this? If it fall out that hee fall into the handes of enemies, let him thinke that God hath brought him into that place,<note place="margin">
                  <p>He that is once caught for religion hath no means to go backe.</p>
                  <p>It is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that we aunſwere to all that the wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of vs.</p>
               </note> &amp; will haue him to be one of the witneſſes of his ſonne, and therefore that there is no way to draw backe, vnleſſe it be in denying our fayth to him, to whom we haue promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all duety: both to liue and to dye, and to whome wee are and belong, although wee had promiſed nothing vnto him. Hereby I doe not binde all men of neceſſitye to make a full and entire confeſſion of all that they beleeue, admit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were therto required, S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this point hath vſed a good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, who was as ready as any other freely to mainteine the cauſe of the goſpel, as he ought. And alſo it was not without cauſe that our Lorde Ieſus promiſed that in ſuche a caſe hee will giue vs a mouth &amp; Wiſedome: as if he ſhould ſay, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the holy ghoſt is not only to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs to be bold and valiant: but alſo to giue vnto vs Wiſdome and diſcretion, to
<pb facs="tcp:16748:17"/>
know howe it becommeth vs to rule and gouerne our ſelues in ſo great and harde a matter.<note place="margin">
                  <p>why Chriſte ſometime helde his peace.</p>
                  <p>It is the rule of chriſtians to confeſſe his faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing required. Chriſt neuer diſſembled to ſaue his life.</p>
                  <p>Roſſe his examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he wrote is here anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>The teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the verity ought more to bee regarded of vs then our life.</p>
                  <p>VVee maye not regarde what other men do, but what they ought to do. Iohn 21.</p>
               </note> The ſumme is, that they which are in ſuch diſtreſſe, ſhould aſk and receiue ſuch Wiſdome from aboue, not following their carnall counſell to ſeeke a waye to eſcape, (as they ſay) by any croſſe or bypathes. There are alſo whiche reply that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, aunſwered not to them that aſked of him. But I ſay firſte of all, that this ſerueth not to aboliſhe the rule which hee hath giuen vs, to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our fayth, when we are thereto re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired Secondly I ſay, that he neuer diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſaue his life. Thirdly that he neuer gaue anſwer ſo doubtful, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it did not import ſufficient witneſſe of that which he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken: or rather, that hee had not ſatiſfied them already which came to aſke him fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it were laying nettes to catch him. Wherefore let this point remaine reſolute amongſt all Chriſtians: that is, that they ought not to account their liues more dear then the teſtimony of the trueth, inaſmuche as God will be glorified in it. Is it in vain that hee calleth all thoſe witneſſes (for the word Martyrs ſignifith the ſame) that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16748:17"/>
haue anſwered to the enemies of the fayth? Is it not becauſe he would haue them ſerue to ſuch purpoſe? And here euery one muſt not looke to his fellow and companion: for God doth not ſhew this honour to al to cal them thereto. And foraſmuch as we are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to marke others,<note place="margin">VVe muſt arme our ſelues with the promiſes of God in our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> the more we ought to take heed thereof. <hi>Peter</hi> hauing hard at the mouth of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, that hee ſhold be led in his old age whither he wold not, aſketh what ſhould become of <hi>Iohn</hi> his companion. There is none of vs but hee would willingly make ſuch a reply. For this we imagine by and by: Why do I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer then others? But contrariwiſe Ieſus Chriſte exhorteth all in generall, and euery one in particular, alwayes to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to the end that as he ſhal call hither one or other, euery man may march forth in his ranke and order. I haue ſhewed before that we ſhall be ill appointed to ſuffer Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vnleſſe that we be armed with Gods promiſes. It remayneth now that we laye out a little more fully wherto they tend, not to ſpecifie al by piecemeale &amp; exactly, but to ſhew the principal things, that God would haue vs to hope for, to the end to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs
<pb facs="tcp:16748:18"/>
in oure afflictions. Nowe theſe are briefly three thinges.<note place="margin">three things ſpecially to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon vnder the croſſe.</note> The firſt is, that foraſmuche as our life and death are in his hande, that he will in ſuch fort preſerue vs by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that not one hayre of our heads ſhall fal but by his licence.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the faythfull ought to holde themſelues aſſured into whoſe handes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſhall come, that God hath not caſt of the ſafegarde whiche hee hath of their perſonnes, If ſuch a perſwaſion were well imprinted in our hearts, we ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the moſt part of doubts and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexities that torment and hinder vs from doing our duety. We ſee that Tyrants are let loſe: and hereupon it ſeemeth to vs that God hath no further meane to ſaue vs: For this cauſe wee are tempted to prouide for our ſelues, as though there were no more wayting vpon him. But contrariwiſe his prouidence which he hath declared vnto vs is ſuch, as ought to be vnto vs an inuinſible fortreſſe.<note place="margin">Our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be in the handes of him who hath created them.</note> Let vs therefore labour to learne this ſhorte ſentence, that our bodies are in his hands who hath created them. For this cauſe hee hath ſometimes deliuered his owne after a miraculous manner,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16748:18"/>
and beyonde all hope of men, as <hi>Sidrach-Miſach</hi> and <hi>Abednago,</hi> from the fiery fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, <hi>Daniel</hi> from the Lyons denne, <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>Herods</hi> priſon, where he was enchai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, fettered &amp; kept ſo ſtraightly. By theſe examples he would teſtifie vnto vs,<note place="margin">God giueth our enemies power ouer vs.</note> that he holdeth our enimies bridled, though it ſeem not ſo, and hath power to drawe vs out, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the mouth and middeſt of death when he will. Not becauſe he always doth it: but by keeping vnto himſelfe the auctho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity of diſpoſing of vs both in life &amp; death, he wold haue vs fully reſolued that he hath vs in his keeping: in ſuche ſort that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer Tyrantes looke, or with what fury ſoeuer they ruſh vppon vs, that it is from him onely who is the orderer of oure life. If he ſuffer Tyrants to kil vs,<note place="margin">Our life i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deare in the ſight of God</note> it is not becauſe our liues are not deare vnto him, and in greater recommendation an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred folde then it is worthy, ſeeing it is ſo, that hee hath pronounced by the mouth of Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. Eſai. 16. our enemie ſhall render accompt of our blood.</note> 
               <hi>That the death of his ſaints is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious before him,</hi> and ſayth hee alſo by the mouth of <hi>Eſay: That the earth ſhal diſcloſe the blood which ſeemed to be bidden.</hi> Let the enemies therefore of the Goſpel, be as
<pb facs="tcp:16748:19"/>
prodigal in ſhedding the blood of his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, as they will, yet ſhall they render a terrible account euen to the laſt and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt drop. They doe ſcornfully mock at this day when they burne the faythful,<note place="margin">The power of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and after they haue bathed them ſelues in their bloode, they are ſo drunken therewith, that they care nothing at al what murders they commit. But if we haue patience to wait, God will ſhew in the ende that it is not in vayne that he hath ſet ſuche an high price vpon our life,<note place="margin">The conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of martirs is the worke of God.</note> In the mean time, if he doth vs no euil, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſerueth to ratifie his goſpel, which in worthineſſe ſurmounteth heauen and earth. And the better to aſſure vs that God leaueth vs not in the handes of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, as hauing forſaken vs, let vs call to minde the ſentence of Ieſus Chriſte, where he ſayth, that it is he whome they perſecute in his members.</p>
            <p>God had well ſayde before by <hi>Zacharie, He that toucheth you, toucheth the ayple of mine eye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A notable example.</note> But this is yet more plaine, that if we ſuffer for the Goſpell, it is as if the Sonne of God were there in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Wherefore let vs knowe that Ieſus Chriſt muſt forget himſelfe, if he ſhould not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16748:19"/>
thinke of vs when wee are in priſon, or in danger of death for his cauſe: And let vs knowe that God taketh to his owne heart all the outrages that Tyrantes doe vnto vs, as if they were faſtened to his owne ſonne.</p>
            <p>Let vs come to the ſecond pointe that God in his promiſes hath ſet forth vnto vs for our conſolation: that is, that he will ſo ſuſteine vs by the power of his holy ſpirite that our enemies whatſoeuer they doe, or Satan their head, yet ſhal they not get the vpper hand ouer vs. And in deede we ſee howe hee diſplaieth his graces in ſuche a neede. For ſuch inuincible conſtancie as is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true martyrs, is a ſufficient ſhew that God worketh mightily in them. There are two grieuous things to the fleſh in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions: too wit, the one the rebukes and ſhame of men, and the other the tormentes that the body endureth. But God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs, ſuche aſſiſtannce that through patience wee ſhall ouercome both the one and the other. And hee perfourmeth in deede that which hee hath promiſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Let vs therefore take this buckler too repulſe and put backe all feares, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:16748:20"/>
we are aſſailed, and let vs not reſtrain the power of Gods ſpirite to ſo narrowe a ſcantling, that wee thinke not, but that hee will eaſily ouercome all mens cruelties. And hereof amongſt others we had an no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example in our time not to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>A certeine yong man who dwelt heere with vs being taken in the citie of <hi>Tournay</hi> was condemned to bee but beheaded if hee recanted: and to be burned aliue, if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his opinion. When he was aſked what he woulde doe, he aunſwered ſimply: He that ſhal giue me grace to dye patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his name, he will giue mee grace to endure the fire. We ought to eſteeme this ſentence not as the ſentence of a mortall man: but as a ſentence of the holy ghoſte, to the end to aſſure our ſelues that God is as able to ſtrengthen vs, and to make vs to ouercome all torments, as to mooue vs to take any other kinde of meeker death in good part. Which is more, wee ſee often times, what conſtancy hee giueth to poore malefactors who ſuffer for theire offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I ſpeake not of the obſtinate: but of thoſe which comfort themſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16748:20"/>
of Ieſus Chriſt, and by this mean receiue with peaceable hearte the moſte grieuous puniſhment that can bee done vnto them: As we may ſee a notable example thereof in the theefe who was conuerted at the death of Chriſt. God who ſo mightely aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth poore offenders, being worthily puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for their miſdeedes, will hee faile his who fighte for his cauſe, that hee will not giue them an inuincible power? The thirde poynt concerning the promiſes that God hath made to his martirs, is of the fruite that they ought to hope for of their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: and in the end if neede be of death it ſelfe. Now this fruite is after that he hath glorified his name, and edified his Church through their conſtancie,<note place="margin">The fruite of our death</note> when they ſhalbe gathered with the Lorde Ieſus Chriſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his immortall glory. But becauſe wee haue ſpoken more fully of it before, it is ynough nowe to bring it in our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let the faythfull learne too lifte vp their heades on highe to this Crowne of Immortalitye and Glorye, whereunto GOD doth call them: to the ende that he doe them no hurte in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:16748:21"/>
them to forſake their preſent life for ſuch a reward: and to be aſſured of this ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable benefite, let them alwayes haue before their eyes the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity which they haue with our Lorde Ieſus, to beholde life in the middeſt of death, as he by the oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brye and ſhame of the Croſſe, came to that glorious reſurrection in which conſiſteth all our felicity, ioy, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16748:21"/>
            <head>An anſwere to the ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>of the papiſtes againſt Chriſts ſyllie</hi> flock, appointed to the ſlaughter <hi>through fire.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>HOW deſperatly, how deſperately</l>
               <l>can thus the papiſtes grone,</l>
               <l>To ſee Gods worde ſo faythfully,</l>
               <l>through fire to be borne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2</head>
               <l>Therfore their teeth &amp; toung they wher</l>
               <l>like a raſer ſo fine,</l>
               <l>Againſt Chriſtes martyrs for to ſpet,</l>
               <l>their poiſon and repine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>And whereof trueth they cannot lay,</l>
               <l>to them that loue the worde,</l>
               <l>With curſſe and lies they doe aſſay,</l>
               <l>to ſhew their learned ſworde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>And when they haue with force falſely,</l>
               <l>condemned that is right.</l>
               <l>Then ſtuddy they full craftely,</l>
               <l>to waſh their handes of ſpight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>It is not we then can they vpholde,</l>
               <l>that any man do kill,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16748:22"/>Leaſt our cold charity be outtolde,</l>
               <l>our ranckor and our yll.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>Therefore wee muſt deuiſe ſtraighte lawes</l>
               <l>Our iudgements to be kept.</l>
               <l>And make the nobility like Dawes,</l>
               <l>ſo be caught in our net.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7</head>
               <l>Thus we in faire places reigne,</l>
               <l>and make good cheere and game,</l>
               <l>To ſee noble men put to payne,</l>
               <l>to execute their ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8</head>
               <l>To them it is a matter ſtaunge,</l>
               <l>to ſee golde fire byde,</l>
               <l>And ſayth to be without exchange,</l>
               <l>when paynes of death betyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>If turne as wether cocks men woulde,</l>
               <l>that goſpell doe profeſſe,</l>
               <l>Then for Catholique men they ſhould</l>
               <l>be counted as they geſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10</head>
               <l>But fayth is a Subſtance playne,</l>
               <l>of thinges that be not ſeene,</l>
               <l>And will in ſtedfaſtneſſe remayne,</l>
               <l>though chaungelings turne &amp; weene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>11</head>
               <l>What though liuely hope they call,</l>
               <l>falſely deſperation,</l>
               <l>Who knoweth not the trueth at all,</l>
               <l>blinded by ſedition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>Was not Chriſte <hi>Belzebub</hi> named,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16748:22"/>becauſe that trueth he ſayd,</l>
               <l>And yet was not to be blamed,</l>
               <l>as euil tongues betrayde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>13</head>
               <l>Now <hi>Ione</hi> of <hi>Kent</hi> and heretike,</l>
               <l>for helpe they in doe call,</l>
               <l>Who in her hereſy did ſticke,</l>
               <l>and died therewithall,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>14</head>
               <l>Who knoweth not the prince of Hell</l>
               <l>to haue his ſeruantes ſtout,</l>
               <l>As wel as the ſincere goſpell,</l>
               <l>profeſſors rounde about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>15</head>
               <l>But in this we differ playn,</l>
               <l>for vs we haue the worde,</l>
               <l>And they for them haue naught certain,</l>
               <l>but onely ſelfe accorde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>16</head>
               <l>Alſo vaynglory they obiect,</l>
               <l>to ſuch as for trueth dye,</l>
               <l>By all meanes they would them reiect,</l>
               <l>whoſe glory is on hie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>17</head>
               <l>That glory is not counted vayne,</l>
               <l>which gloryeth in the Lorde.</l>
               <l>And for the ſame to abide great payn.</l>
               <l>it is after the word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>18</head>
               <l>Iudge therefore with equity,</l>
               <l>and call not trueth amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Leaſt for your great impiety,</l>
               <l>ye leeſe the endleſſe bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>19</head>
               <l>O noble men of famous England,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16748:23"/>looke well to your doings,</l>
               <l>Let not partakers be your handes,</l>
               <l>of guiltleſſe bloodſheddings,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>20</head>
               <l>No drop of Faythfull bloodſhed is,</l>
               <l>through rage of cruelneſſe,</l>
               <l>Which God will not require as his,</l>
               <l>repent therefore and ceaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS quod I. P.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16748:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
